I was not planning on making another
video on covered calls, but my last two
videos started a lot of discussion that
I think is worth pursuing. There are a
ton of these products being launched in
Canada, and I believe people are making
serious errors in their assessments of
them. I feel a personal responsibility
to give some final comments. I think the
best way to approach this is to respond
to comments from my last video. I'll
address whether covered calls protect
you in a downturn, whether the new age
of covered call funds are better than
the old ones, whether I have any
integrity, and why I keep coming back to
this topic. I'm Ben Felix, chief
investment officer at PWL Capital, and
I'm going to tell you one last time why
covered calls are destructive to
long-term wealth, even if you need
income from your portfolio.
The financial product landscape has come
full circle. For decades, actively
managed mutual funds siphoned dollars
out of investor pockets and into the
financial industry without offering much
if anything in return. Eventually,
investors started to realize that paying
2% or more to own actively managed
mutual funds sold by commission
salespeople was a losers game. At first,
that led people toward lowcost index
funds slowly, which was a good thing.
But now, high fee products that look
different enough from traditional
actively managed mutual funds while
carrying many of the same issues are
being promoted by unlicensed financial
content creators. I have a lot of
sympathy for the people using these
products, being being sold on these
products. They're being sold hope.
They're being sold a better future, but
I don't think they understand the true
costs. I want to read you a quote that
has stuck with me since I read it a few
weeks ago. Capitalists respond to the
actual demand for their products, not
the demand that would exist if people
were perfectly rational and truly
understood their own best interests.
Since people's demands are driven by the
benefits they perceive rather than the
benefits they actually get, the
financial system supplies too many
products with exaggerated benefits and
too few products with underappreciated
benefits. And since perceived costs
rather than actual costs drive people's
demands, the financial system supplies
too many products with hidden costs. I
need you to think about that. It comes
from John Campbell's new book, Fixed.
Campbell's a professor at Harvard and
one of the top living financial
economists. He's basically saying that
capitalism doesn't work properly when
people don't know which products are
good for them or how much those products
cost. When it comes to covered call
funds, people seem to want them because
they are so psychologically attached to
income, even when the income comes in a
package that makes them worse off.
Overall, capitalists, the the fund
companies are more than happy to meet
this demand because they can launch
products that cater to investor biases
while charging a high fee for the
service. There's no money to be made in
lowcost index funds. So, it's not
surprising to see this shift. Something
I didn't appreciate when I started
making videos on covered calls is that
there is a whole cottage industry of
unlicensed financial content creators
promoting these products and in many
cases selling access to coaching
sessions or research to help you build
your covered call income portfolio.
Financial markets and financial advice
are regulated for a reason. Regulation
in Canada has not been perfect and our
long history of high fee actively
managed funds being sold on commission
is a blemish that will take decades to
recover from. But taking advice from
unregulated content creators with
limited financial background is risky
business. There's nothing inherently
wrong with selling options. Where I take
issue is with these products being
marketed and sold on their yields as if
the yields were returns when in reality
the yields are at best irrelevant and
more likely have a negative relationship
with expected returns. Okay, on to the
comments. Let's start with covered calls
in down markets. In my last video, I
showed five examples of covered call
funds underperforming their underlying
equities when monthly withdrawals are
held constant at the distribution yield
of the covered call fund. In those
examples, the investor in the covered
call fund and the underlying fund were
spending the same dollar amount at the
same time intervals. I did include the
2022 downturn in my previous examples.
Going back further, the Invesco S&P 500
buy ETF started in December 2007 just in
time for the great financial crisis. I
set up a similar side-by-side comparison
of the covered call fund and an S&P 500
index fund. Spending from both
portfolios in this simple model is
matched to the distributions of the
covered call fund. To be completely
clear, both sides of the comparison are
spending the same dollar amounts which
is based on the covered call funds
distributions. Keeping in mind that this
is one of the worst periods for the US
stock market in recorded history, we do
see that the covered call strategy is
helpful. It slightly reduces the
downside. However, the covered call fund
quickly falls behind as equities
recover. The option premiums from
selling calls are creating a bit of a
buffer when stocks are down. But writing
those options into an eventual recovery
is destructive to wealth because they
limit upside participation. Over the
full history of this fund, including the
great financial crisis, the COVID crash,
and the 2022 decline, and holding
spending constant for the covered call
fund and the underlying equity fund, an
investor in the underlying would have
3.8 8 times the amount of wealth as an
investor in the covered call strategy at
the end of September 2025. What is not
relevant here is whether or not you had
to sell shares in a down market to fund
your spending. This is a tough one to
grasp, but it's really important. Let's
look at JAPI as an example. I will walk
through this in excruciating detail. I'm
sorry and you're welcome. Let's step
back in time to May 2020. JP Morgan
launches the JP Morgan Equity Premium
Income ETF. You have a bit of extra
stimulus cash kicking around. So, you
buy $1 million of JAPI. I know that's a
ridiculous amount for stimulus cash, but
bear with me. That that's 20,000 shares
of JAPI at at the share price at that
time. You spend all the monthly
distributions from JAPI, but you don't
touch your 20,000 shares. Your neighbor
puts $1 million into IVV, the iShares
Core S&P 500 ETF on the same day. That
amounts to 3,355
shares of the ETF and a little bit of
cash left over. Your neighbor matches
all the spending that you're doing from
your JAPI distributions through a
combination of of IV's quarterly
dividends and selling off shares of IVV
each month. For example, your first
distribution from JAPI is $9,882
while your neighbor receives a $4,230
dividend and sells 17 shares of their
ETF to bring their total cash, their
total spending cash roughly in line with
yours. Fast forward to September 2022
and IVV is down a lot from its recent
peak. You receive an $11,178
dividend from JAPI while your neighbor
has to sell 28 shares at a depressed
price to match your spending. This seems
really bad for your neighbor, but what
happens next is important. Your neighbor
continues to sell IVV shares to fund
their spending, but the value of their
remaining shares is increasing faster
than they spent. You still have 20,000
shares of JAPI, but their value has
barely increased since you bought them.
Keep in mind that you and your neighbor
have spent the same dollar amount from
the portfolios. Covered calls were
successful in this example at avoiding
selling shares in a downturn, but they
also capped upside participation
significantly, resulting in less wealth
overall, holding spending constant. I
saw a lot of comments saying, "Well,
what if you sell your last shares to
fund your spending?" To which I would
ask, what if the value of your constant
number of shares declines to zero? Two
different ways to arrive at the same
outcome. It's the number of shares
multiplied by the price that matters.
Either one on its own contains very
limited information. As these examples
show, covered calls do offer some
protection in a falling market due to
the option premiums generated by selling
calls. But I can't tell you when the
market will fall or more importantly,
when it will recover. I get the appeal
of living off the income in a down
market. But when the cost of that income
is missing out on expected returns both
before and potentially more importantly
after a stock price decline, it is
increasing, not decreasing the risk of
your ability to pay your bills in the
future. Remember, covered calls look a
lot like holding a large portion of your
portfolio in cash. That can look good
over some periods when stocks perform
poorly, but in the long run, it is
expected to be very expensive. Another
interesting question is whether
reinvesting rather than spending the
distributions gives covered calls a
magical advantage in a market downturn.
As Andy suggests in a comment, as you
can see here, with dividends reinvested,
it does not make a difference to the
general story. Covered calls continue to
dramatically underperform when both
sides of the comparison are left to
accumulate and reinvest their
distributions. One of the mistakes I
think a lot of people are making with
these products is thinking, as Andy
suggests, that covered calls allow you
to spend more in retirement or retire
sooner with less savings. The only way
this is true is if there was no other
way, psychologically speaking, for you
to spend your own money. That aside,
covered calls result in lower, not
higher, sustainable spending for
long-term investors for the simple
reason that they reduce expected
returns. Addressing the questions about
when covered calls may or may not shine
was important. There were also a ton of
comments from people claiming that I
picked the wrong funds to analyze in my
previous videos. The interesting thing
to me is that most of the tickers that
people offered up as superior performers
and better representations of covered
call funds as a strategy have similarly
underperformed their underlying
equities. These repeated interactions
led me to believe with all due respect
to everyone watching that many investors
have no idea what their investment
returns actually are. And that is an
observation backed up by academic
research. People really don't know what
their returns are, which makes it hard
to make good decisions. Let's go through
all the examples that I was given. These
first ones are US-listed ETFs. SPYI, the
NEOS S&P 500 highinccome ETF, has
trailed the Vanguard 500 index fund by
4.61% annualized since August 2022. Not
off to a good start here. QQQI, the NEOS
NASDAQ 100 high-inccome ETF, has trailed
the Invesco NASDAQ 100 ETF by 2%
annualized since January 2024. Not as
bad. JPQ, the JP Morgan NASDAQ equity
premium income ETF, has trailed the
Invesco NASDAQ 100 ETF by an annualized
4.36% since May 2022. To its credit, in
the 2022 downturn, JAPQ did better than
its underlying, but any advantage was
short-lived as it gave up the upside in
the subsequent recovery. Okay, DIVO, the
Amplify CWP enhanced dividend income
ETF, if I have any integrity, I had to
put some effort into the underlying
comparison here since DIVO is not an
index fund. It holds a portfolio of
highquality dividend oriented stocks.
So, it doesn't make sense to compare it
to, say, an S&P 500 ETF. I compared it
to the Vanguard Dividend Appreciation
Index Fund ETF. They have moderate
holdings overlap and a very high return
correlation. So, I think it's a
reasonable comparison. DIVO has
underperformed by an annualized 51 basis
points since December 2016. I know I
said an S&P 500 comparison made no sense
here, but DIVO has performed far worse
against that benchmark for whatever
that's worth. QQQI we did earlier.
Another underperformer. At least I still
have my integrity. Ah, okay. Income and
growth. Let's take a look. Hyld is the
Hamilton Enhanced US Covered Call ETF.
This is a Canadian listed ticker. Let's
keep in mind that this fund does have a
modest 25% cash leverage. It aims to be
a higher yielding alternative to the S&P
500 with similar volatility. So, I will
compare it to an S&P 500 ETF hedged to
Canadian dollars since HyLD is also
hedged. It has underperformed by 0.9%
annualized since February 2022.
HD div, the Hamilton enhanced multis
sector covered call ETF, is a portfolio
of primarily sector covered call ETFs
with a sector mix intended to be broadly
similar to the S&P TSX60. It has beaten
the S&P TSX60 as proudly proclaimed on
the fund website, but this fund has a
third of its assets invested in US
equities. To make a proper comparison, I
did my best to reconstruct an index fund
portfolio matched to the underlying
equities of HDIV. My model had no
leverage while HDIV has cash leverage of
25%. My model outperforms HD since
inception. Properly benchmark, I don't
think this fund is beating anything.
It's levering up for more downside
volatility and still underperforming.
There is an interesting discussion point
here. This fund and its underlying
equities are different from a Canadian
market index and a US market index and
they have beaten both since inception. I
would tend to say this type of
short-term performance is unlikely to
repeat in the long run. The evidence
against active management's ability to
beat the market in the long run is
absolutely overwhelming. I would
approach short-term performance like
this with extreme caution. And note that
if you believe in this specific sector
and country mix, getting exposure to it
without covered calls would be cheaper
and have higher expected returns. The
same thing goes for HHIS, the Harvest
Diversified High Income Shares ETF. It
is an equally weighted portfolio of 15
trending companies using covered calls
and 25% leverage. This fund has not been
around long and for the first few months
of its life, it only had nine holdings.
All of its holdings are single stock
covered call ETFs from Harvest. I ran
the portfolio of underlying stocks with
no leverage and no covered calls. My
waitings won't match perfectly, but I
find that the underlying stocks have
performed about the same as the fund. In
other words, you were not any better off
from the leverage and covered calls in
HHIS compared to just owning the same
stocks directly over this relatively
short period. If I allow 25% leverage
for the underlying stock portfolio, it
has outperformed HHIS significantly,
which again is exactly what we should
expect when the effects of covered calls
are isolated. Now, to be fair here, HHIS
has beaten indexes like the NASDAQ 100
and the S&P 500. But let's keep in mind
that we are talking about a fund that
has existed since January 2025, has had
as few as nine holdings, and currently
has only 15 holdings. It would be
exceptionally rare for a concentrated
portfolio of attention-grabbing stocks
like this to deliver outperformance over
an extended period of time. The vast
majority of professional active managers
underperform index funds in the long
run. I see people online putting their
faith into these products and I find it
really concerning. I honestly hope I'm
proven wrong, but at the very least, I
hope that people recognize the risk they
are taking. This is not a free lunch.
Okay, that's the full tour of
performance comparisons. Fundamentally,
a covered call changes the shape of the
distribution of expected returns in a
way that I think is detrimental to
long-term investors. And this shows up
clearly in the data. Lastly, I want to
address why I keep making videos on this
topic. I have nothing to sell you by
telling this information. If you listen
to what I'm saying in these videos,
you'll invest in lowcost total market
index funds, which I have nothing to do
with personally or professionally,
rather than high-cost covered call
funds, which I also have nothing to do
with personally or professionally. So,
why am I doing this? Understanding
complex financial products, both
analytically and psychologically, is a
huge part of my job as the chief
investment officer at PWL Capital. And I
don't know if you know this, but telling
strangers on the internet what you think
you know about something is one of the
best ways to assess and strengthen your
knowledge. I actually gain a lot from
making these videos and engaging in the
discussions that follow. More
altruistically, I want to see a
financial product marketplace in Canada
that isn't overwhelming, intimidating,
or dangerous for people who are just
starting out. The way that a lot of
financial products, not just covered
call funds, just a lot of financial
products, the way they're marketed and
sold makes it really confusing for
investors to understand what they're
buying, but also what they should be
buying. Covered calls are a particularly
challenging example because they cater
to the strong mental accounting bias
that many investors have. by providing
fundamental information and basic
performance comparisons rather than
marketing hype. I hope these videos help
a few people make better decisions or at
the very least help them ask the right
questions. Thanks for watching. I'm Ben
Felix, chief investment officer at PWL
Capital. I'm going to leave this topic
alone for a while now, but I hope that
we can keep the conversation going.